A Guide to the Mark B. Hardin Papers, 1849-1947
Virginia Military Institute Archives
Archives, Preston Library, Virginia Military Institute
Mark B. Hardin Papers 1849-1947
Archives, Preston Library, Virginia Military Institute
mss 00440
The collection consists of 20 items.
Administrative Information
Access
There are no restrictions.
Biographical/Historical Information
Mark Bernard "Bunny" Hardin, son of Lauriston Bonaparte Hardin and Anna M. H. Hooe, was born at Alexandria, Virginia on August 14, 1838. He entered the Virginia Military Institute on September 7, 1854 and graduated on July 4, 1858, standing first in his class. Following graduation he joined the faculty at VMI, teaching Chemistry and other subjects until the beginning of the Civil War.
Hardin served with the 33rd and 9th Virginia Infantry Regiments and with the 18th Battalion Virginia Heavy Artillery. He was captured at Sayler's Creek on April 6, 1865 and held at Old Capitol and Johnson's Island prisons. He was released on oath July 3 (some records say June 27) 1865.
Following the war, Hardin established an analytical chemistry business in New York City, where he resided until July 1867. He accepted a position as Professor of Chemistry at his alma mater, VMI, in the summer of 1867, and remained at the Institute until September 1890. From September 1890 until 1910 he taught at Clemson University.
Hardin married Mary Massie Payne of Wareenton, Virginia, on August 4, 1869. The couple had 8 children (4 sons and 4 daughters). He died at Clemson, South Carolina, on April 26, 1916. He is buried at the Old Stone Church Cemetery, Clemson.
Scope and Content Information
The Mark B. Hardin papers contain twenty letters. The bulk of the correspondence was written by Hardin to his siblings, Susan Lane Hardin and John Haywood Hardin, during the period 1864-1899. In addition to family and personal news, the letters touch on various aspects of Hardin's career (Civil War service, VMI Faculty member).
Arrangement
The papers are arranged in chronological order.
Contents List
- Mark B. Hardin Papers, 1849-1947, 20 items of correspondence
  All letters were written by Mark B. Hardin (MBH) unless otherwise noted.
  - MBH to Augusta Lane Hardin (stepmother), 1849 April 21
    Childhood letter, written at Washington, DC; containing family news.
  - MBH to Susan Hardin, 1864 January 3
    Civil War letter. Written from Battery 8, Richmond, Virgnia. References to war service and family news.
  - B. Hooe to Susan Hardin, 1865 June 19
    Written at Elizabeth, New Jersey. MBH's grandfather Hooe is writing for first time after resumption of mail communications; laments separation of families caused by war; references to MBH situation as prisoner of war.
  - W. P. Johnson to Susan Hardin, 1865 June 25
    When M. B. Hardin was taken prisoner, the family swung into action to obtain his release. MBH had grown up in Washington and had extensive famiy there. Dr. W. P. Johnston, an uncle and a physician of some influence, wrote this letter to Susan Hardin. He also mentions the status of her father's estate, which was tied up in court prior to the Civil War.
  - B. Hooe to Susan Hardin, 1865 June 29
    From "Grandpa Hooe" written at Elizabeth, New Jersey. Regarding MBH's pending release from prison, and her father's estate.
  - MBH to Susan Hardin, 1865 July 10
    Written from Washington, DC. Regarding estate of their father, Lauriston Bonaparte Hardin.
  - MBH to Susan Hardin, 1865 August 9
  - MBH to Susan Hardin, 1865 September 7
  - B. Hooe to Susan Hardin, 1865 September 26
    Written from Elizabeth, NJ. Family news; more on the estate of her father.
  - MBH to Susan Hardin, 1866 July 25
    Written from New York City, where Hardin was attempting to start a consulting chemist business.
  - MBH to Susan Hardin, 1867 June 6
    Written from Alexandria, Virginia. Hardin is considering accepting a faculty position as Professor of Chemistry at the Virginia Military Institute.
  - MBH to Susan Hardin, 1867 July 28
    Written from Lexington, Virginia. Has accepted teachng position at VMI.
  - MBH to Susan Hardin, 1867 November 2
    Written from Lexington, Virginia. Mentions attending family wedding in Alexandria; VMI making progress on restoration of war-damaged barracks.
  - MBH to Susan Hardin, 1867 December 6
    Written from Lexington, Virginia. Regarding Susan's engagement to James Berrien MacPherson.
  - MBH to Susan Hardin, 1868 January 18
    Written from Lexington, Virginia. References to Susan's upcoming marriage.
  - MBH to Susan Hardin, 1873 January 23
    Family news; sent picture of his son, Lauriston; information about Susan's mother's grave.
  - MBH to John Hardin, 1895 May 7
    Written from Clemson College, South Carolina. Enclosing money for Montgomery Co. property taxes.
  - MBH to John Hardin, 1897 September 28
    Written from Clemson College, South Carolina. Family news; Montgomery Co. property taxes.
  - MBH to John Hardin, 1899 March 24
    Written from Clemson College, South Carolina. Family news.
  - J. A. Pinckney to C. C. Chadburn, 1947 January 18
    Written from Holy Trinity Church, Clemson, SC. Regarding Hardin family mmemorial window.